What's up, TikTokers?  Are you rushing through the last
days of your vacation?  Run to the nearest beach
or your favorite
mountain spot.  And don't forget sunscreen,
an umbrella, and a good read to pass
the time.  Or even better, your phone to
watch this compilation of the best characters
from Greek mythology.  We
assure you that these stories, even though
they're centuries old, are just as gruesome
and exciting as any current adventure book
or television series.  See for
yourself the myths of Persephone,
the Griffin, Pandora's Box, the Phoenix,
and Nemesis.  And don't forget to tell us in the
comments which one is your favorite, or ask us for
new ones.  Ready to travel to Olympus...?
In today's video, we'll talk about the myth of
Persephone, also known as Kore, a goddess
from Greek mythology.  He was the deity of
vegetation and brought fertility to the
fields.  But at the same time she was the queen
of the Underworld, and carried out the curses
of men on the souls of the dead.
Throughout history, the Greeks found
an explanation for the phenomenon of the four
seasons. Do you want to know it?
Persephone was born to Zeus, father of the gods
and king of Olympus, and Demeter, the mother goddess
of agriculture.  The origin of its name
is not very clear.  It may come from the
form “Persephatta,” which means “she
who cleans the wheat.”  But it could also
come from the expression “Pherein phonon,”
which means “she who brings death.”  There
are also several versions of his story,
but the most complete is the one that appears in
one of the “Homeric Hymns” by the
poet Homer himself.  Specifically, in the “Hymn
to Demeter” it is said that Persephone used to
live with her mother, away from the rest of the
gods of Olympus.  Despite this, she stood out
so much for her beauty that she had several suitors.
Among these were Hermes, the god of ingenuity,
Ares, the god of war, Apollo, the god of the arts,
and Hephaestus, the god of fire and the forge.
However, her mother Demeter rejected all
gifts and marriage proposals, and hid
her daughter from the other Olympian deities.
One of those who was most infatuated with
Persephone was Hades, god of the Underworld,
the realm of the dead.  He decided to ask
his brother Zeus, Persephone's father, for permission
to marry her and he got it.  But
Demeter would never allow her daughter to descend
to the Underworld, so he planned to kidnap her
and take her with him to his domain.
One day Persephone was innocently picking
flowers in a field in Enna, on the island of
Sicily.  Apart from some nymphs, he was accompanied by
Athena, goddess of wisdom, and Artemis,
goddess of animals.  As he bent down
to pick a daffodil, there was a pop and
a crack opened in the ground.  From her
sprang Hades, who unopposed mounted
Persephone in his chariot and took her to the Underworld.
The nymphs were turned into sirens as punishment for not having intervened
.  And poor
Demeter was devastated.  She abandoned everything to
tirelessly search for her daughter
across the ends of the earth, aided by
the torches of Hecate, the deity of roads
and virgin lands.
As the goddess of agriculture,
Demeter's obsession naturally had an effect on
nature.  According to some versions, he prohibited
the land from being sown.  In others, she simply
neglected her role as the mother of agriculture,
plunged into despair, and the fields
lost their fertility.
Hecate suggests to Demeter that she ask
Helios, the all-seeing personification of the sun
, what had happened,
and he finally reveals the whereabouts of
her daughter.  Zeus, pressured on one side by the
cries of humans, hungry for
the lack of crops, and on the other by the crying
of Demeter, agreed and decided to intervene.
He ordered Hades to free Persephone,
sending Hermes, god of wit, to rescue her.
Hermes negotiated hard with Hades, and finally
managed to convince him.  One of the conditions
for Persephone to be able to leave the Underworld
was that she not consume food from there.
And indeed, in the sadness of his captivity, he
had refused to eat.
But before she could leave the Underworld,
Hades tricked her into eating six
pomegranate seeds.  Hermes
successfully brought her back, but as punishment for
eating food from the Underworld, Persephone
was forced to return every year, one month
for each seed she had eaten.
From then on, he would spend six months each year
on Olympus with his mother and the
other six months in the Underworld with
Hades.  When Demeter and her daughter were together,
the earth flourished with vegetation.  But the
other half of the year became
a barren land again.  And this is how the
ancient Greeks explained the cycle of the
four seasons and their effect on nature.
Aside from this, Persephone also appears
in many other classical myths such as the story
of Orpheus, the musician who descended into the
underworld to recover his dead wife.
Persephone is so moved by hearing him play
that she allows them to return to earth again.
Or in the myth of Adonis, a young man so beautiful
that Aphrodite herself, goddess of beauty,
fell in love with him.  She was the one who sent him
to Persephone to take care of him, but she
didn't count on the fact that the queen of the Underworld would
also become obsessed with him and refuse
to return him.  The dispute was resolved by
Zeus who decided that Adonis should spend part
of the year with each of them.
Persephone appeared in numerous works of
classical Greek art.  She is usually dressed
in a robe and carrying a bundle of hay,
although she may also hold a scepter or a
small box.  She was also the protagonist,
along with her mother, of the Eleusinian Mysteries,
rituals held at the time
of sowing, in which her
return to the earth was celebrated, and which promised her
faithful a better destiny in the Underworld.
The myth of Persephone, besides being so
interesting, is one of the clearest ways
to see how the Greeks related to
their gods, and above all how they tried to
find an interpretation for phenomena
that had no explanation.
Surely many of you know that there was a
mythological creature called a griffin.  But
did you know that it was also the one that gave its name
to water taps?  We'll explain
why, but first, let's learn a little more about
this fearsome beast.
Its name comes from the Greek “gryphos”,
which means curved or hooked, and in turn
derives from the Persian “shirdal” which means
“lion-eagle”.  And this being has
the front part of a giant eagle, with
golden feathers, a sharp beak and powerful claws.
While on its back it is like
a lion, with yellow fur, muscular
legs and a long tail.  He is also often depicted
with pointy ears or feathers at the end
of his tail.
Its qualities were said to be eight times
larger and stronger than a common lion,
and with its powerful claws it was perfectly
capable of capturing a rider on horseback or a
pair of cattle.  Their nails, the
size of an ox's horn, were the
most prized trophy since they could be used to
make cups and changed color if
poison was poured into them.  Although their ribs were
also used to make powerful
archery bows.  He
possessed a very keen sense of vision,
and for some ancient cultures he also had
the power to control the four
natural elements.  He was able to breathe fire through
a hole near his nose and expel
freezing air through his mouth.  The wind produced
by the beating of its wings could generate
tidal waves, and its powerful roar could
make the earth tremble.
Griffins are mentioned in many
ancient cultures, and although their exact origin is unknown, they
appear to have first appeared
in the Near East, in the paintings and sculptures
of the ancient Babylonians, Assyrians, and Persians.  They
also appeared in the legends of
Ancient Greece, where they were consecrated
to the god Apollo, pulling his chariot on the
daily journey he undertook from East to West.
and as guardians of their treasure.
For their part, the Romans associated them with
Nemesis, the goddess of revenge.  During
the Middle Ages, the legend changed, and they became
the inhabitants of some coveted mountains
in northern India, which had large
reserves of gold and which they guarded
zealously to protect the nests of their young.  They
were also a common resource in the decoration
of Gothic churches, transformed into gargoyles,
and in heraldic shields, as an emblem
of families, representing strength,
courage and vigilance.
In fact, today it is believed that the myth
of the griffins may have originated from the discovery
of fossil remains of dinosaurs belonging
to the Ceratopsidae family.  This species
had a beak-like mouth, large
scapular bones, a long tail, and hoofed feet,
and was abundant in the deserts of Central Asia.
If any of those ancient civilizations
came across the remains of one of these creatures, they
must have thought it was a legendary being.
Now, how did these grotesque creatures come
to give their names to
water faucets?  Very simple.  As we told you,
taps became a common artistic element
in architecture.  In addition to
building facades, they were widely used to
shape public water fountains.
And it was precisely these sources that
ended up creating the term "tap",
referring to the water outlet.
Curiously, this term does not appear in the
rest of the Latin languages.  Most of them
use derivatives of the form “robinet,”
which comes from the French “robin,” which designates
sheep.  And in this country,
fountains used to be decorated with ram
or sheep heads.  You
know, TikTokers, the next time
you turn on a tap, consider that you could be
unleashing the fury of a fearsome mythological creature.
Hello TikTokers!  Do you remember the joke we
played on you last April Fool's Day?
Many of you wrote to us wanting to know
the rest of the story behind Pandora's Box,
so today we finally decided to
open it.  Pay attention!  This
is one of the great legends of
Greek mythology and is part of the story
of Pandora, the first woman on Earth.
The most famous version was the one written
in the 7th century BC by the poet Hesiod.
And it is a story of revenge, that of Zeus against
men and the Titan Prometheus for stealing
the sacred fire and giving it to them.
The father of the gods became angry and
ordered Hephaestus to model
the first woman out of clay.  Each of the gods
gave him a gift: Athena gave him wisdom,
Apollo music, Aphrodite beauty, and Hermes
eloquence.  Zeus himself breathed
life into her and gave her the name Pandora, which means
"she who has the gifts."
She was offered as a wife to Prometheus, who
rejected her knowing that after her betrayal,
any gift from Zeus would be a trap.
So he then took her to his
brother Epimetheus, who despite the warnings
decided to marry her.
As a wedding gift, Pandora received an
oval jar (pithos), not a box (pyxis)
as is often said, but a translation error
caused this confusion.  He was also given
specific orders not to open it under any
circumstances.
But among all their gifts, the gods
had also granted Pandora great
curiosity, so she decided to open the jar
anyway to see what was inside.  In
doing so, all the
misfortunes and evils that invaded our
world escaped from within.  Old age, illness, madness,
vice, sadness, poverty, crime...
all spread irremediably.  Only
one last thing remained hidden in the background:
hope.
Pandora, realizing what she had done,
regretted it greatly and wanted to try to fix
the harm she had caused.  He dedicated himself to
wandering the world offering all
men that hope that was the only thing he had
left.
The truth is that the myth of Pandora
perfectly shows the entirely masculine vision
that was held in classical Greece, and in
general in the ancient world.  The woman who
is curious and disobeys man is to blame
for all evils.  And it also recalls the
origin of the world according to the Christian Bible,
where Eve ate the forbidden apple, and because of
her, evils were unleashed.
Aside from this, it became very popular in
Western culture, and was even the origin
of colloquial expressions like "opening
Pandora's box," when we mean that
an action will unleash serious consequences.
Or “hope is the last thing to be lost”
referring to the only thing left inside
the box.
The myth of Pandora is continued by
her own daughter, Pyrrha, who married Deucalion,
the son of Prometheus.  When Zeus decided to
punish men by flooding the earth
with a great flood, they were the only
survivors, and they decided to go consult
the oracle on how they could repopulate the Earth.
He told them that they should throw
their mother's bones along the road over
his shoulder.  Deucalion did not understand this
profanation, but Pyrrha clarified that by
“mother” she meant Gaia, the Earth itself,
and that her bones were the rocks themselves.  Thus
the stones they threw became
men if they were thrown by Deucalion, or
women if they were thrown by Pyrrha.
This makes us all descendants
of Pyrrha.  And at the same time, Pandora, the first
woman, who, despite having accidentally unleashed evil
, should also be remembered
as the “grandmother” of humanity and guardian
of hope.
One of the mythological creatures that
has aroused the most interest for generations
is the Phoenix;  A bird whose characteristics
have fascinated hundreds of cultures and peoples
throughout history, as it is a
universal symbol of rebirth and immortality.
The word phoenix comes from the Greek term
phoinix (φοίνιξ), which means “
red in color.”  This creature is usually represented
as a huge bird wrapped in flames,
with a golden body and scarlet wings, whose
plumage emits a great glow.  He had
great stamina, control over fire, and
infinite wisdom.  But without a doubt its
most representative feature is the power to burn
and rise from its ashes.
Some fables claim that the Phoenix lived
in the deserts of Arabia, near a well
of fresh water where it bathed every
day and sang a beautiful song.  Although
the truth is that its origins cannot be located
in a single point on the map since this creature
is common to many civilizations, which have
built their own legends around it
.  Thus we can find representations
of the phoenix in China, Central America and Egypt.  It is
in this last country that we find
the first mythological references through
the Greek historian Herodotus.  For the
ancient Egyptians, the equivalent of the Phoenix
was the Bennu, a sacred bird similar to a
heron, with long legs and two large feathers
on its head like a crest.  The Egyptians
associated it with the flooding of the Nile,
the Sun, death and rebirth.  It was
a creature that believed it was necessary to
renew itself from time to time in order to acquire
greater wisdom.  That's why every 500 years he would build
a nest with beautiful aromatic branches, and while
singing a beautiful song he would set it on fire
and burn with it until he was consumed by the
flames.  After three days, a new Bennu
rose from the ashes, stronger and wiser.  He
then took his remains to Heliopolis,
to the temple of the god Ra, beginning a new
cycle of life with which to inspire the
Egyptian people.
On the other hand, we have the Christian version,
in which the Phoenix was a noble creature
with strong principles that was born
in the Garden of Eden, under the Tree of
Good and Evil.  It is said that when Adam and
Eve were expelled, the angel who banished them
fired a spark that set fire to the
bird's nest, burning it to a crisp.  But because the Phoenix
maintained its honor and refused to taste the
forbidden fruit, it was granted immortality,
and instead of dying it gained the power to rise
from its ashes.
Its mission ever since has been to transmit
the wisdom it has harbored since its origins
in Eden, and to serve as an inspiration to all
those seeking knowledge.  But
in addition to this gift, she also possessed the gift of
strength, and it was said that her tears were
healing.
Over time, this creature has
become the image of physical
and spiritual rebirth, personifying the power of
fire, which purifies and grants immortality.
And in the same way it represents the Sun, which dies
at the end of each day to reappear at the
next dawn.  It is
also currently considered a symbol
of resilience, that is, our ability
to overcome difficult situations and adapt
to them.  That's why today it's common to hear
expressions like "rising from the ashes"
or "reborn like the Phoenix," highlighting
the strong symbolism this creature still
holds for humanity.
Hello, TikTokers!  We know from your comments
that you're a big fan of Greek mythology, and you're
always asking us to make videos about
legendary figures from this culture.
Well, today we bring you one of the most
requested stories: the story of the
goddess of justice, Nemesis.
This goddess does not have a very clear origin.  Numerous
sources present her as the daughter of Erebus and
Nyx, the gods of darkness and night,
although others describe her as the daughter of Oceanus
or Zeus.  But all agree that Nemesis
is part of the first generation of
primordial deities, which in Greek mythology
refers to the gods who have existed since
the beginning of the world, and who are usually
identified with natural elements or principles
.
This is because their parents, Erebus and Nyx,
were born from Chaos, one of the four
primordial entities along with Gaia, Tartarus
and Eros, and which for the Greeks symbolized
"everything that existed before the gods
and elemental forces", that is, the
primitive state of the cosmos.
The origin of the name Nemesis comes
from the Greek verb “némein” (νέμειν),
which means “to distribute”, a clear
reference to her virtues as a goddess.  Because
within Greek mythology, Nemesis was
the goddess of revenge, balance, and
retributive justice.
This consisted of applying the
same punishment to the offender.  In other words: if a
person killed another, the sentence was the
same for the guilty party, in this case, death;
a kind of “eye for an eye.”  Although
our criminal justice system is completely
different today and seeks to compensate for the harm caused,
in the ancient world retributive justice
was a very important concept.
Nemesis was also in charge of punishing
human excesses and lack of moderation
, pride and arrogance.  And to
put a stop to the chaos, he had to apply
harsh punishments to the mortals who had
been too favored by the goddess Fortuna.
However, with his intervention he managed to
maintain the balance of the universe, another
key concept in the Greek interpretation
of the cosmos.
Since she is one of the symbols of justice, she is
usually represented with the branch of an apple tree,
with a scale or a sword in her left hand.  She
also usually wears a crown, and sometimes
a veil that covers her head.  Although
Nemesis does not play a leading role in
Greek fables, he does appear in a
supporting role in numerous stories, always
as a character charged with maintaining
balance among the actions of others.
One of the many stories tells that Zeus was
captivated by her beauty, although she did
not reciprocate his love.  To escape him, she changed
shape countless times, until
one day she turned into a goose.  However,
Zeus transformed into a swan and pursued her
relentlessly until he was able to seize
her.
From this union Nemesis laid two eggs, from
which the twins Castor and Pollux
and the beautiful Helen were born.  It is believed that the
latter's decisive role, which triggered the
Trojan War, was given by Nemesis herself,
as a kind of revenge for
Zeus's abuses.
Another story in which Nemesis appears is that
of Croesus, the last king of Lydia, whose
reign was marked by pleasures and
excesses.  Faced with this, the goddess decided to
lead him on a dangerous expedition in
which he had to confront King Cyrus of Persia.
After the adventure, Croesus ended up ruined and
unhappy, proving that no mortal can
be too lucky to avoid upsetting
the universal balance.
In Greek mythology there is also the
figure of Themis, the Titaness of
divine justice.  Although in contrast to Nemesis,
she was more serene, and was in charge of establishing
order and guiding men towards the right
path.  That is why those who ignored
Themis's advice ended up meeting Nemesis,
who appeared to them to apply a furious
punishment.
Curiously, nowadays we often use
the word nemesis to refer to an enemy
or rival, probably in reference to this
goddess who, despite embodying justice,
represents its most irrational side.  So
be careful with your actions, TikTokers,
because Nemesis's vengeance could fall
upon you...